Tyler Dewar: The way I feel right now
تايلور ديوار : الطريقة التي اشعر بها الآن
is that all of the other speakers
هي ان جميع المتحدثين الآخرين
have said exactly what I wanted to say.
قالوا بالضبط ما اردت قوله .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it seems that the only thing left for me to say
و يبدو ان الشئ الوحيد الذي تبقى لي لقوله
is to thank you all for your kindness.
هو شكرا لكم جميعاً للطفكم.
TD: But maybe in the spirit
ت. د. : ولكن ربما في الروح
of appreciating the kindness of you all,
من تقدير للطفكم جميعا،
I could share with you
يمكنني مشاركتكم
a little story about myself.
قصة صغيرة عن نفسي.
TD: From the time I was very young, onward,
ت. د. : منذ ان كنت صغيرا جدا ، وما بعده،
I was given
أُعطيت
a lot of different responsibilities,
الكثير من المسئوليات المختلفة،
and it always seemed to me, when I was young,
ودائما ما بدا لي ، عندما كنت صغيرا،
that everything was laid out before me.
كل شي وضع قبلي.
All of the plans for me were already made.
جميع الخطط لأجلي كانت قد وضعت بالفعل.
I was given the clothes that I needed to wear
لقد أٌعطيت الملابس التي أحتاج ان البسها.
and told where I needed to be,
وقيل لي ما احتاج ان اكون.
given these very precious
أُعطيت ذلك الثوب الغالي
and holy looking robes to wear,
المقدس الشكل لإرتدائه.
with the understanding
للتفاهم
that it was something sacred or important.
انه شيء مقدس أو مهم.
TD: But before that kind of formal lifestyle happened for me,
ولكن قبل أن أدخل هذه الحياة الرسمية .
I was living in eastern Tibet with my family.
كنت اعيش في التبت الشرقية مع أسرتي.
And when I was seven years old,
وعندما كنت في السابعة من عمري .
all of a sudden,
فجأةً ،
a search party arrived at my home.
مجموعة بحثية وصلت لموطني.
They were looking the next Karmapa,
كانوا يبحثون عن الكارمابا القادم،
and I noticed they were talking to my mom and dad,
لاحظت انهم يتحدثون مع امي وأبي.
and the news came to me that they were telling me
وأتتني الاخبار بأن اخبروني
that I was the Karmapa.
أنني الكارمابا.
And these days, people ask me a lot,
وهذه الأيام ، يسألني الناس كثيرا،
how did that feel.
كيف جعلك ذلك تشعر؟
How did that feel when they came and whisked you away,
كيف شعرت عندما اتوا واخذوك بعيدا،
and your lifestyle completely changed?
وتغير شكل حياتك نهائيا؟
And what I mostly say is that,
و أغلب ما اقوله هو
at that time,
انه في ذلك الوقت
it was a pretty interesting idea to me.
لقد كانت فكرة مثيرة جدا لي.
I thought that things would be pretty fun
ظننت انها ستكون ممتعة جدا
and there would be more things to play with.
وانه سيكون هناك الكثير من الاشياء للعب بها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
TD: But it didn't turn out to be so fun and entertaining,
ت.د. : لكن تبين انها ليست ممتعة ولا مسلية،
as I thought it would have been.
كما تخيلتها ستكون.
I was placed
لقد وضعت
in a pretty strictly controlled environment.
في بيئة ذات رقابة صارمة.
And immediately,
وعلى الفور ،
a lot of different responsibilities,
الكثير من المسئوليات المختلفة،
in terms of my education and so forth, were heaped upon me.
من حيث دراستي وهكذا دواليك ، كانت تنهال على عاتقي.
I was separated, largely, from my family,
لقد فصلت عن عائلتي بشكل كبير،
including my mother and father.
بمن فيهم امي و ابي.
I didn't have have many personal friends
لم يكن لدي العديد من الاصدقاء الشخصيين
to spend time with,
لقضاء الوقت معهم،
but I was expected to perform
ولكن كان متوقع مني ان أؤدي
these prescribed duties.
هذه الواجبات المنصوص عليها.
So it turned out that my fantasy
لذا تبين أن خيالي
about an entertaining life of being the Karmapa
عن كون حياة الكارمابا مسلية
wasn't going to come true.
لم يكن ليصبح حقيقة.
It more felt to be the case to me
لقد شعرت ان الحال بالنسبة لي
that I was being treated like a statue,
اقرب لأنني ساٌعمل كتمثال،
and I was to sit in one place
كان علي الجلوس في مكان واحد
like a statue would.
كالتمثال.
TD: Nevertheless, I felt that,
ت. د. : على الرغم من ذلك، شعرت بأنه ،
even though I've been separated from my loved ones --
رغم أنني فصلت عن أحبائي --
and, of course, now I'm even further away.
و طبعاً انا الآن أبعد من ذي قبل
When I was 14, I escaped from Tibet
عندما كنت في الرابعة عشر ، هربت من التبت
and became even further removed
وصرت أبعد
from my mother and father,
عن أمي وأبي،
my relatives, my friends
اقربائي ، أصدقائي
and my homeland.
و وطني.
But nevertheless,
ولكن مع ذلك،
there's no real sense of separation from me in my heart,
ليس هناك شعور حقيقي من الانفصال عنهم في قلبي،
in terms of the love that I feel
من حيث الحب الذي أشعر
for these people.
لهؤلاء الاشخاص.
I feel, still, a very strong connection of love
شعرت بأنه ما زال هناك رابط حب قوي
for all of these people
لكل هؤلاء الناس
and for the land.
وللوطن.
TD: And I still do
ت. د. : ومازلت
get to keep in touch with my mother and father,
على اتصال بامي وابي،
albeit infrequently.
وإن كان نادرا.
I talk to my mother
تحدثت الى أمي
once in a blue moon on the telephone.
مرة عند كل قمر ازرق (إشارة لندرة الحدوث) في الهاتف.
And my experience is that,
ومن تجربتي تلك
when I'm talking to her,
عندما تحدثت معها
with every second that passes
في كل ثانية تمر
during our conversation,
أثناء محادثتنا،
the feeling of love that binds us
شعور الحب الذي يربطنا
is bringing us closer and closer together.
يقربنا ويقربنا لبعضنا.
TD: So those were just a few remarks
ت. د. : لذا كانت تلك مجرد بضع ملاحظات
about my personal background.
عن خلفيتي الشخصية.
And in terms of other things that I wanted to share with you,
وفيما يتعلق بالأمور الاخرى التي أردت أن أشارككم بها،
in terms of ideas,
من حيث الأفكار،
I think it's wonderful to have a situation like this,
وأعتقد أنه لأمر رائع أن نكون في هذا الوضع،
where so many people from different backgrounds and places
حيث هناك العديد من الاشخاص من خلفيات واماكن مختلفة
can come together,
يمكنهم الاجتماع معا،
exchange their ideas
وتبادل افكارهم
and form relationships of friendship with each other.
ويشكلون علاقات وصداقات مع بعضهم البعض.
And I think that's symbolic
وأعتقد أن ذلك رمزيا
of what we're seeing in the world in general,
لما نراه في العالم عموما،
that the world is becoming smaller and smaller,
ان ذلك العالم يصير اصغر واصغر،
and that all of the peoples in the world
و ذلك لجميع الناس في العالم
are enjoying more opportunities for connection.
يتمتعون بفرص اكثر للتواصل.
That's wonderful,
هذا رائع،
but we should also remember
لكن يجب علينا ان نتذكر ايضا
that we should have a similar process happening on the inside.
ان تكون لدينا ايضا عملية مشابهة تحدث داخليا.
Along with outward development
جنبا إلى جنب مع التنمية الخارجية
and increase of opportunity,
وزيادة فرصنا،
there should be inward development
يجب ان تكون هناك تنمية داخلية
and deepening of our heart connections
وتعميق صلات قلوبنا
as well as our outward connections.
كصلاتنا الخارجية.
So we spoke and we heard some
تحدثنا وسمعنا بعضا
about design this week.
عن التصميم هذا الاسبوع.
I think that it's important for us to remember
واعتقد انه من المهم لنا ان نتذكر
that we need
اننا نحتاج
to keep pushing forward
لنستمر بدفع
on the endeavor
مساعي
of the design of the heart.
تصميم القلب.
We heard a lot about technology this week,
لقد سمعنا الكثير عن التكنلوجيا هذا الاسبوع،
and it's important for us to remember
ومن المهم لنا ان نتذكر
to invest a lot of our energy
إستثمار الكثير من طاقاتنا
in improving the technology of the heart.
لتحسين تكنلوجيا القلب.
TD: So, even though I'm somewhat happy
ت. د. : لذا، على الرغم من انني سعيد الى حد ما
about the wonderful developments that are happening in the world,
عن التنمية الرائعة التي تحدث في العالم،
still, I feel a sense of impediment,
مازلت ، اشعر بعائق،
when it comes
عندما يتعلق الأمر
to the ability that we have
بقدرتنا
to connect with each other on a heart-to-heart, or a mind-to-mind, level.
على التواصل مع بعضنا على مستوى من القلب للقلب او من العقل للعقل.
I feel that there are some things
أشعر أن هناك بعض الأشياء
that are getting in the way.
التي تعوق الطريق نحو ذلك.
TC: My relationship
ت. د. : علاقتي
to this concept of heart-to-heart connection, or mind-to-mind connection,
بمفهوم التواصل من القلب للقلب أو من العقل للعقل،
is an interesting one,
علاقة مثيرة.
because, as a spiritual leader, I'm always attempting
لأنه ، كقائد روحي ، حاولت دائما
to open my heart to others
ان افتح قلبي للآخرين
and offer myself up
وأعرض نفسي
for heart-to-heart and mind-to-mind connections
لتواصل من القلب للقلب و من العقل للعقل
in a genuine way with other people,
بطريقة حقيقية مع أشخاص آخرين ،
but at the same time,
ولكن في نفس الوقت،
I've always been advised
دائما نصحت باني
that I need to emphasize intelligence
أحتاج ان أشدد على الذكاء
over the heart-to-heart connections,
على مدى إتصالات القلب للقلب،
because, being someone in a position like mine,
لأن ، شخصا في مثل منصبي،
if I don't rely primarily on intelligence,
إذا كان لا يعتمد في المقام الاول على الذكاء،
then something dangerous may happen to me.
يمكن أن يحدث شيئا خطيرا لي.
So it's an interesting paradox at play there.
لذا انها مفارقة مثيرة تجري هنا.
But I had a really striking experience once,
ولكن كانت لي تجربة مذهلة حقا ذات مرة،
when a group from Afghanistan
عندما مجموعة من الافغان
came to visit me,
أتت لزيارتي،
and we had a really interesting conversation.
وكان لدينا محادثة مثيرة للاهتمام حقا.
TD: So we ended up talking about the Bamiyan Buddhas,
ت.د. : وهكذا انتهى بنا في الحديث عن تماثيل بوذا في باميان،
which, as you know,
الذي، كما تعلمون،
were destroyed some years ago in Afghanistan.
دمرت منذ بضع سنوات في أفغانستان.
But the basis of our conversation
ولكن أسس حديثنا
was the different approach to spirituality
كانت من وجهات نظر روحانية مختلفة
on the part of the Muslim
من جهه تقاليد اسلامية
and Buddhist traditions.
و تقاليد بوذية
Of course, in Muslim,
بطبيعة الحال ، للمسلم
because of the teachings around the concept of idolatry,
وبسبب التعليم حول المفاهيم الوثنية
you don't find as many
لا تجد الكثير
physical representations of divinity
من التمثيلات البدنية للالوهية
or of spiritual liberation
أو التحرر الروحي
as you do in the Buddhist tradition,
كما تجدها في التقاليد البوذية,
where, of course, there are many statues of the Buddha
حيث، بطبيعة الحال ، هناك العديد من التماثيل لبوذا
that are highly revered.
تبجل كثيرا
So, we were talking about the differences
لذا، كنا نتحدث عن الخلافات
between the traditions
بين التقاليد
and what many people perceived
ويتصور الكثير من الناس
as the tragedy of the destruction of the Bamiyan Buddhas,
ومأساة تدمير تماثيل بوذا في باميان،
but I offered the suggestion
ولكني قدمت اقتراحا
that perhaps we could look at this in a positive way.
ربما يمكن أن ننظر إلى هذه المسألة بطريقة إيجابية.
What we saw in the destruction of the Bamiyan Buddhas
ما شهدناه في تدمير تمثالي بوذا في باميان
was the depletion of matter,
كان أستنفاذ للمسألة
some solid substance
بعض المجسمات الصلبة
falling down and disintegrating.
سقطت وتفككت.
Maybe we could look at that to be more similar
ربما يمكن أن ننظر إلى ذلك كأنه أكثر قرباً
to the falling of the Berlin Wall,
لسقوط جدار برلين,
where a divide
حيث الانقسام
that had kept two types of people apart
الذي فصل بين نوعين من الناس
had collapsed and opened up a door
قد أنهار وفتح الباب نحو
for further communication.
مزيد من التواصل.
So I think that, in this way,
لذلك أعتقد أنه في هذا الطريق،
it's always possible for us
انه من الممكن دائما بالنسبة لنا
to derive something positive
لاستخلاص شيء إيجابي
that can help us understand one another better.
التي يمكن أن تساعدنا على فهم بعضنا بعضا بشكل أفضل.
TD: So, with regard to the development
ت. د. : لذا، وفيما يتعلق بالتنمية
that we've been talking about
والتي كنا نتحدث عنها
here at this conference,
هنا في المؤتمر
I really feel
حقيقة اشعر
that the development that we make
أن التطور الذي نصنعه
shouldn't create a further burden
وينبغي ألا تخلق عبئا جديدا
for us as human beings,
بالنسبة لنا كبشر،
but should be used
ولكن ينبغي أن تستخدم
to improve
لتحسين
our fundamental lifestyle
أسلوب حياتنا الاساسي
of how we live in the world.
في كيف نعيش في هذا العالم.
TD: Of course, I rejoice
ت. د. : بالطبع انا مبتهج
in the development and the growth and the rise
في التنمية والنمو والارتقاء
of the noble land of India, the great country of India,
لأرض الهند النبيلة ، للهند العظيمة,
but at the same time, I think,
ولكن في نفس الوقت، كما أعتقد ،
as some of us have acknowledged,
كما اعترف بعض منا،
we need to be aware
يجب ان نكون مدركين
that some aspects of this rise
أن بعض جوانب هذا الرقي
are coming at the cost
تأتي على حساب
of the very ground
هذه الارض
on which we stand.
هذه الارض التي نقف عليها
So, as we are climbing the tree,
لذا ونحن نتسلق الشجرة
some of the things that we're doing
بعض الأشياء التي نقوم بها
in order to climb the tree
من أجل تسلق الشجرة
are actually undermining
في الواقع إضعاف
the tree's very root.
جذور الشجرة.
And so,
ولذا،
what I think it comes down to
ما اعتقد انه يصل اليه
is a question of, not only having information of what's going on,
ليست مسألة ما نملكه من معلومات عما يحدث
but paying attention to that
ولكن ان نلتفت الى
and letting that shift our motivation
ان نجعل هذا التحول هو دافعنا
to become more sincere
لنصبح اكثر مصداقية
and genuinely positive.
وايجابيا حقيقة
We have hear, this week,
لقد سمعنا هذا الاسبوع،
about the horrible sufferings, for example,
عن معاناة رهيبة، على سبيل المثال،
that so many women of the world
الكثير من نساء العالم
are enduring day-to-day.
يثبتن يوما بعد يوم
We have that information,
لدينا هذه المعلومات ،
but what often happens to us
ولكن ما يحدث لنا في كثير من الأحيان
is that we don't really choose to pay attention to it.
هو أننا لا نختار حقا أن نولي ذلك اهتماما .
We don't really choose to allow that
نحن حقيقة نختار ان لا نمكن ذلك
to cause there to be a shift in our hearts.
ليكون سبب تحول في قلوبنا
So I think the way forward for the world --
لذا فإنني أعتقد أن الطريق إلى الأمام بالنسبة للعالم --
one that will bring the path of outer development
ذلك الذي من شأنه ان يجلب مسار التنمية الخارجي
in harmony
في التناغم
with the real root of happiness --
مع الجذور الحقيقية للسعادة
is that we allow
هو أن نسمح
the information that we have
للمعلومات التي لدينا
to really make a change in our heart.
لإجراء تغيير حقيقي في قلوبنا
TD: So I think that sincere motivation
ت. د. : لذلك اعتقد ان الدافع الصادق
is very important for our future well-being,
مهم جدا لمستقبلنا المترف
or deep sense of well-being as humans,
أو احساسنا المترف كبشر,
and I think that means sinking in
واعتقد ان هذا يعني الانغمار في
to whatever it is you're doing now.
ما تفعله الآن مهما كان.
Whatever work you're trying to do now to benefit the world,
أيا كان العمل الذي نحاول القيام به الآن لصالح العالم،
sink into that,
إستغرق في ذلك,
get a full taste of that.
إحصل على طعمه الكامل.
TD: So, since we've been here this week,
ت. د. : وهكذا ، منذ كنا هنا هذا الاسبوع،
we've taken millions of breaths, collectively,
لقد اتخذنا الملايين من الأنفاس، بشكل جماعي ،
and perhaps we haven't witnessed
وربما لم نشهد
any course changes
اي مضمار تغيير
happening in our lives,
يحدث في حياتنا،
but we often miss the very subtle changes.
ولكن نفتقد في كثير من الأحيان التغييرات الطفيفة جدا.
And I think
وأنا أعتقد
that sometimes we develop
في بعض الأحيان أن نطور
grand concepts
المفاهيم الكبرى
of what happiness
لكيف يمكن ان
might look like for us,
تبدو السعادة بالنسبة لنا
but that, if we pay attention,
ولكن ، إذا أولينا اهتماماً
we can see that there are little symbols of happiness
يمكننا أن نرى أن هناك القليل من رموز السعادة
in every breath that we take.
في كل نفس نأخذه.
TD: So, every one of you who has come here
لذا ، كل واحد منكم أتى هنا
is so talented,
موهوب جدا،
and you have so much to offer to the world,
ولديكم الكثير لتقدموه للعالم
I think it would be a good note to conclude on then
وأعتقد أنه سيكون من الجيد ان اختم اليوم بملاحظة ثم
to just take a moment
لأخذ لحظة
to appreciate how fortunate we are
لتقدير كم نحن محظوظون
to have come together in this way and exchanged ideas
لإجتماعنا سوية هنا وتبادل الافكار
and really form a strong aspiration
و للطموح القوي حقا
and energy within ourselves
و الطاقة التي بداخلنا
that we will take the good
التي ستأخذ الجيد
that has come from this conference,
الذي أتى من هذا المؤتمر،
the momentum, the positivity,
الزخم، والإيجابية،
and we will spread that and plant it
وسوف ننشر ذلك ونزرعه
in all of the corners of the world.
في كل اركان العالم.
His Holiness the Karmapa: Tomorrow is my Talk.
قداسته الكارمابا : غداً حديثي.
TD: Lakshmi has worked incredibly hard,
ت. د. : لاكشمي عمل بصعوبة لا تصدق،
even in inviting me,
حتى في دعوتي،
let alone everything else that she has done
فعلت كل شئ لوحدها
to make this happen,
لتجعل هذا يحدث
and I was somewhat resistant at times,
كنت معارضا في بعض الاحيان،
and I was also very nervous throughout this week.
وكنت ايضا عصبيا هذا الاسبوع.
I was feeling under the weather and dizzy and so forth,
كنت تحت شعور الطقس وبالدوار وهكذا دواليك ،
and people would ask me, why.
وكان الناس يسألونني : لماذا.
I would tell them, "It's because I have to talk tomorrow."
وأود أن أقول لهم، "لانني سأتحدث غدا".
And so Lakshmi had to put up with me through all of that,
ولذا كانت لاكشيمي معي خلال هذا كله.
but I very much appreciate
لكني أقدر كثيرا
the opportunity she's given me
الفرصة التي أعطتني إياها
to be here.
لأكون هنا
And to you, everyone, thank you very much.
وأنت (تايلور ديوار) ، الجميع ، شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
HH: Thank you very much.
قداسته : شكرا جزيلا